{"tossups": [{"question": "This man was spotted laughing at the romantic scenes between Sergei and Katerina and shuddering in disgust at loud orchestra hits during a performance of <em>Lady Macbeth of the</em> <em>Mtsensk District</em>. This man\u2019s artistic views were enforced by his cultural censor, Andrei  Zhdanov. An attempt to mend fences with this man was subtitled \u201cA Soviet Artist\u2019s Reply to Just  Criticism.\u201d For the point, name this dictator who clashed with Dmitri Shostakovich while leading the USSR in the 1950s.", "answer": "Joseph <b><u>Stalin</u></b> [or Ioseb Besarionis je <b><u>Jugasvili</u></b>]", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This man, who was New York\u2019s only delegate to the Constitutional Convention, commanded an artillery battery at the Battle of Trenton. He advocated growing a national debt and  patronizing the creation of industry in his <em>Report on Manufactures</em>, issued during his time as the first Secretary of the Treasury. This man was the primary author of the Federalist Papers. For the point, name this Federalist leader who was killed while dueling with Aaron Burr and is seen on the ten-dollar bill.", "answer": "Alexander <b><u>Hamilton</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This speech describes all kings as \u201cGrasshoppers\u201d. This oration is best read as a refutation of Solomon Stoddard\u2019s Half-Way Covenant, and it frequently caused listeners to faint or run away shrieking with its images of a \u201cloathsome insect\u201d being held over a fire, symbolizing man\u2019s precarious position with God. For the point, name this speech first given in Enfield in 1741, which defined the First Great Awakening and was delivered by Jonathan Edwards.", "answer": "\"<b><u>Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God</u></b>\"", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "As part of this larger initiative, farmers were encouraged to beat pots and pans together every morning to flush out birds, which could then be killed. Its Four Pests Campaign included the disastrous Sparrow Killing Campaign, which led to flourishing insect populations. Juvenile pigs were placed together for breeding and the rural peasantry was taught to make unusable steel in backyard furnaces during this disastrous initiative. For the point, name this 1950s push to immediately modernize China, which triggered widespread famine.", "answer": "<b><u>Great Leap Forward</u></b> [or <b><u>Four Pests</u></b> Campaign until it is read]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The FKA became the exclusive supplier to this mission\u2019s target for the next twenty-nine months as a result of the outcome of this mission, which led to the largest ground search of all time. Victims of this event, whose body parts were found in Texas and Louisiana, included the Israeli Ilan Ramon as well as Kalpana Chowla and commander Rick Husband. This event was caused by wing damage and compromised heat protection that occurred when a chunk of foam detached at liftoff. For the point, identify this 2003 disaster which destroyed a Space Shuttle.", "answer": "destruction of the <em><b><u>Columbia</u></b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "James Ionsin funneled money appropriated for this program towards basic research instead, and Carol Rosin coined the derisive name which became permanently attached to this program. This program, which was effectively phased out in 2002 after being subsumed into the BMDO in 1993, was to rely on \u201cx-ray lasers\u201d and may have been a ruse to cause an economic war with the USSR. For the point, identify this 1980s program advocated Ronald Reagan which was to use space-based stations to shoot down enemy missiles.", "answer": "<b><u>Strategic Defense Initiative</u></b> [or <b><u>Star Wars</u></b>; or <b><u>SDI</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A candidate in this year\u2019s election was attacked for his close association with Russian mystic Nicholas Roerich, and left his position as publisher of <em>The New Republic</em> to run. Another candidate in this election ran on a ticket with Fielding Wright after walking out of a major party  convention following Hubert Humphrey\u2019s speech. Henry Wallace\u2019s Progressives and Strom  Thurmond\u2019s Dixiecrats were factors in this election, whose outcome was wrong in the <em>Chicago</em> <em>DailyTribune</em>. For the point, name this Presidential election in which Dewey did not defeat Truman.", "answer": "United States Presidential election of 19<b><u>48</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Trains have been carried across this lake since the 1960s on the ferries <em>Uhuru</em> and <em>Umoja</em>. Another ferry on this lake, the <em>Bukoba</em>, sank in 1996, with a loss of over eight hundred lives.  This lake\u2019s <em>Haplochromis</em> cichlid was made extinct by eutrophication, and its other  environmental issues include the invasive water hyacinth. This lake was first encountered by a European in 1858, when John Speke determined it was the source of the White Nile. For the point, name this east African lake which Speke named for the reigning British monarch.", "answer": "Lake <b><u>Victoria</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This composer expanded his \u201cLibera Me\u201d into a full-scale mass in memory of Alessandro Manzoni, which became his often-performed Requiem. This composer\u2019s name was used as a coded rallying cry for the Risorgimento and the installation of Victor Emmanuel as king. This composer\u2019s historical work includes <em>The Sicilian Vespers</em>, though he is more known for an opera  in which \u201cLa Donna e Mobile\u201d is performed. For the point, name this Italian composer of <em>Rigoletto</em> and an opera set in ancient Egypt, <em>Aida.</em>", "answer": "Giuseppe <b><u>Verdi</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This empire was known to the Greeks as the domain of \u201cSandracottus,\u201d and it made a treaty with the Seleucid Empire that allowed it to incorporate Arachosia and Gandara. This empire was ruled by a man who set up both \u201crock\u201d and \u201cpillar\u201d edicts following the conquest of Kalinga.  This empire briefly became a source of Buddhist missionaries following the conversion of emperor Ashoka. For the point, name this Indian empire that began in the 320s BC under Chandragupta and lasted until 185 AD.", "answer": "<b><u>Maurya</u></b>n Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "After Gillis Duncan was accused of being one of these people, they were tortured at the Old  Tolbooth during the North Berwick trial in Scotland. These people were sought by the \u201chunter general\u201d Matthew Hopkins and by Catholics who used the handbook <em>MalleusMaleficarum</em>. These people were identified by being bound to a board and tossed into water, and they were  \u201chunted\u201d in an early modern \u201cmania.\u201d For the point, name these nonexistent people who were persecuted for their alleged dark magical powers in Europe.", "answer": "<b><u>witch</u></b>es", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Laws designed to protect this process were gutted in the court ruling in the <em>U.S. v.</em>  <em>Cruikshank</em> case. The Brooks-Baxter War caused the end of this process in Arkansas, and this process was demonized in the 1920s by the Dunning School. This process went ahead without either the Ironclad Oath or the Wade-Davis Bill, but was nonetheless vigorously advocated by men such as Zachariah Chandler and Thaddeus Stevens. The Compromise of 1877 ended this period. For the point, name this time period in which the federal government attempted to rebuilt Southern society on an equal basis.", "answer": "<b><u>Reconstruction</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This crime was solved by matching a fragment of wood to the ladder from which it came, by a team under the father of Gulf War general Norman Schwarzkopf. The mysterious \u201cJafsie\u201d was an accomplice to this crime, which began in Hopewell, New Jersey and probably was a bungled attempt to secure a ransom payment. In a possible case of immigrant scapegoating, Bruno Hauptmann was executed for this crime. For the point, name this 1932 event in which the son of a renowned trans-Atlantic pilot was found dead.", "answer": "<b><u>Lindbergh baby kidnapping</u></b> [or <b><u>Lindbergh baby murder</u></b>, etc.]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This policy was limited to a specific set of valid intentions in a case arising from city contracting, 1989\u2019s <em>Richmond v. Croson</em>. This policy was modified in two 2003 cases brought against Lee Bollinger, which held that it could not be blanketly applied as a points benefit. The original case dealing with this policy was Allan Bakke\u2019s lawsuit against the University of California. For the point, name this policy under which traditionally discriminated-against groups receive preferences in hiring or admissions.", "answer": "<b><u>affirmative action</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "For the point, name this former Carlisle Indian School star known as \u201cthe world\u2019s greatest athlete\u201d.", "answer": "Jim <b><u>Thorpe</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This action succeeded after at least three failed attempts which blew up pillows, servants, and serving trays in the Winter Palace. This action led to the Trial of the Fourteen and to the construction of the Church of the Savior of Spilled Blood on the spot where it occurred. This act  was perpetrated by a \u201cpropaganda of the deed\u201d arm of Land and Liberty known as the People's Will, and it prevented the signing of the Loris-Melikov Constitution. For the point, identify this 1881 event in which the emancipator of the serfs died.", "answer": "<b><u>assassination</u></b> [or <b><u>murder</u></b>, etc.] of <b><u>Alexander II</u></b> [prompt on answers that only say <b><u>Alexander</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this city, a longtime advocate of siphoning Owens Valley water was discredited by the dramatic failure of the St. Francis Dam. This city, whose infrastructure in the early twentieth century was designed by William Mulholland, faced another man-made disaster in the early 2000s when the Rampart Squad was revealed to have fabricated evidence, ten years after rioting in this city on the acquittal of Rodney King. For the point, name this oft-troubled California city, which is beset by smog on Rodeo Drive and in Hollywood.", "answer": "<b><u>Los Angeles</u></b> [or <b><u>L.A.</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A never-used Kodak-built backup component for this device is on museum display, as the Ritchey\u2013Chr\u00e9tien Cassegrain reflector built by Perkin-Elmer ultimately worked as promised. The null corrector in this device had to be replaced prior to its taking an image of hundreds of seemingly brightly colored blotches known as its Deep Field. In 2018, this device will be retired and replaced with the new James Webb model. For the point, name this telescope which was placed into Earth\u2019s orbit in 1990.", "answer": "<b><u>Hubble</u></b> Space Telescope [or <b><u>HST</u></b>]", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "This painting depicts a fictitious scene from the \u201cThree Glorious Days.\u201d This painting shows a symbolic Phrygian cap as well as the national embodiment Marianne, who is bare-chested and carrying the tricolor and a musket. The pile of bodies in this painting are the victims of the July Revolution which installed Louis-Philippe and deposed Charles X and the Bourbons. For the point, name this painting of French events in 1830 by Eugene Delacroix (deh-lah-KWAH).", "answer": "<em><b><u>Liberty Leading the People</u></b></em> [or <em>La</em> <em><b><u>Liberte Guidant le Peuple</u></b></em>]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A dying Daniel Webster was carried into the Senate chamber on a litter to speak in favor of  this law, which got Webster condemned as \u201cIchabod\u201d in a John Greenleaf Whittier poem. This law ended the slave trade in Washington, D.C. and created New Mexico and Utah as territories.  The main thrust of this law was admitting California as a free state in exchange for increased Northern aid in returning fugitives to the south. This omnibus bill was signed by Millard Fillmore. For the point, what last great North-South compromise was signed eleven years before the outbreak of the Civil War?", "answer": "<b><u>Compromise of 1850</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This disease radiated out from Calcutta in 1817 in the first of its seven canonical pandemics.  This disease was stopped by removing the handle of the Broad Street pump in 1854 after pioneering epidemiology work by John Snow. A glass of water infected with this disease was used to commit suicide by Peter Tchaikovsky. For the point, name this disease that commonly kills in unsanitary conditions by causing dehydration through constant diarrhea.", "answer": "<b><u>cholera</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "Modern people using the name of this empire are a subgroup of Arab Christians who were killed along with Armenians in one of the three Ottoman genocides. This empire was ruled by Sennacherib, whose \u201cdestruction\u201d was the subject of a poem by Lord Byron. This empire\u2019s Black Obelisk records the conquests of Shalmaneser III. This empire collected a great mass of stone  tablets at Nineveh, creating the world\u2019s first library under Ashurbanipal. For the point, name this empire which dominated the Middle East from the 1100s to 800s BC.", "answer": "<b><u>Assyria</u></b>n empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One of this author\u2019s last pieces of nonfiction was a rumination on the Atlanta child murders of the 1980s entitled <em>The Evidence of Things Not Seen</em>. He criticized racial militancy in another  essay collection, which followed his novel about the \u201cthreshing floor\u201d at the Temple of the Fire Baptized. He also fictionalized his own homosexuality in <em>Giovanni\u2019s Room</em>. For the point, name this author of the political essay volume <em>The First Next Time</em> who created John Grimes in his novel <em>Go Tell It on the Mountain.</em>", "answer": "James <b><u>Baldwin</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "An organizer of this event drew on a very similar demonstration that he had led in 1941 to  advocate for better treatment of sleeping car porters. Bayard Rustin\u2019s role in this event was sometimes minimized due to his Communist affiliations, and another leader of this event, John Lewis, is now a longtime Congressman from Georgia. This event centered on a speech about the  \u201ctable of brotherhood.\u201d For the point, name this 1963 demonstration \u201cfor jobs and freedom\u201d at which the \u201cI Have a Dream\u201d speech was delivered by Martin Luther King, Jr.", "answer": "1963 <b><u>March on Washington</u></b> for Jobs and Freedom", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "As a result of this event, Matthew Killroy was convicted of manslaughter, but Thomas Preston was acquitted. Defenses for this event focused on the insults and snowballs hurled by the victims. Samuel Gray and James Caldwell were killed after an undetermined voice shouted \"Fire and be damned\" at this event. John Adams defended the soldiers involved in this event, where Crispus Attucks also died. For the point, name this 1770 event in which British soldiers killed colonial demonstrators.", "answer": "<b><u>Boston Massacre</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This company began as the frame manufacturer Greco Products. This company was the subject of a court case which specifically noted nonapplicability to discrimination law. Sylvia Burwell was the nominal defendant in that case, brought by this business's founder, David Green, This closely held company said that its religious beliefs prohibited funding emergency  contraception. For the point, name this crafts store that was the subject of a Supreme Court case exempting it from certain portions of the Affordable Care Act in 2014.", "answer": "<b><u>Hobby Lobby</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The <em>Telephone Herald</em>, the world\u2019s longest running telephone newspaper, was founded in this empire. Its joint institutions were indicated by the abbreviation <em>K.u.K.</em> This empire was formed by the 1867 <em>Ausgleich</em> and was dismantled after World War One, which started after the assassination of its heir, Franz Ferdinand. For the point, name this Dual Monarchy ruled by the Habsburgs that had its primary capital at Vienna and its secondary capital in Budapest.", "answer": "<b><u>Austria-Hungary</u></b> [or <b><u>Austro-Hungarian</u></b> Empire; or The Kingdoms and Lands Represented<u> in the</u> <b><u>Imperial C</u><u>oun</u><u>cil and</u></b><u> the Lands o</u>f the Hungarian Holy <b><u>Crown of St.</u></b> <b><u>Stephen</u></b>; or <em><b><u>Osterr</u></b><b><u>eichisch-Ungarische</u></b><u> M</u>onarchiein</em>; or <em><b><u>Osztrak-Magyar</u></b></em> <em><u>Monarchia</u></em>; or <b><u>Dual</u></b> <b><u>Monarc</u><u>hy</u></b> b<u>efore it is read; or</u> <em><b><u>Kaiserlic</u></b><b><u>h und Koniglich</u></b></em> <em><u>Monarchiein,</u></em> <b><u>Im</u><u>perial and Roy</u><u>al</u> </b><u>Monarchy,</u>and <b><u>K.u.K.</u></b> Monarc<u>hy before it is read;</u> <u>promp</u>t on <b><u>Austria</u></b>n <u>Empire; prompt on</u> <b><u>Habsburg</u></b> Mon<u>archy o</u>r <b><u>Hapsburg</u></b> Empire]  <u>[Patrick Li</u>ao]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s dismissal of Africa from his theories is often summed up by claiming he believed  \u201cAfrica has no history.\u201d This man claimed that \u201cworld historical individuals\u201d such as Napoleon seize the \u201cZeitgeist.\u201d This author of <em>Theses on the Philosophy of History</em> provided the basis for  Marxism, which grew out of a circle of \u201cYoung\u201d followers of this man, with his description of dialectical materialism. For the point, name this dense German philosopher of <em>The</em>  <em>Phenomenology of Spirit</em> and <em>The Philosophy of Right</em>.", "answer": "Georg Wilhelm Friedrich <b><u>Hegel</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This movement was essentially the same as the publishers of <em>ThePolarStar</em> and was split into the Northern Society and Southern Society. One of its failed proposals was to institute a Bolivarian dictatorship led by Sergei Trubetskoy. In the only significant action of this  movement, three thousand soldiers rallied in St. Petersburg for \u201cConstantine and constitution,\u201d trying to prevent the accession of Nicholas I. For the point, name this 1825 Russian uprising which took place in a namesake month.", "answer": "<b><u>Decembrist</u></b> Uprising/Revolt", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s king threatened to abdicate rather than approve a law legalizing abortion in  the 1950s. This country was home to Leon Degrelle\u2019s Rexist movement, a native Fascist party. The \"Royal Question\" referendum eventually re-admitted this country\u2019s king Leopold III, who had surrendered to Germany during World War II. For the point, name this country which forms an economic union with the other Low Countries, Luxembourg and the Netherlands.", "answer": "<b><u>Belgium</u></b> [Kingdom of <b><u>Belgium</u></b>; or Royaume de <b><u>Belgique</u></b>; or Koninkrijk <b><u>Belgie</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man was succeeded by Goodwin Knight as governor of California. Abe Fortas was a failed nominee to replace this man in another post. George Wallace denounced this man as  unable to \u201ctry a chicken thief.\" This man, who was the running mate of Thomas Dewey in 1948, chaired the commission investigating JFK\u2019s assassination. For the point, name this Eisenhower appointee as Chief Justice who oversaw several desegregation cases in the 1950s.", "answer": "Earl <b><u>Warren</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was president when <em>banlieue</em> riots erupted after the deaths of two Algerian teenagers in a power station, and Maxime Brunerie attempted to kill him with a knife. He was  prime minister in the \u201ccohabitation\u201d government with Francois Mitterrand. He went to a runoff with the National Front\u2019s Jean-Marie Le Pen to win re-election in 2002. For the point, name this center-right President of France from 1997 to 2007, denounced by American Republicans for opposing the Iraq war.", "answer": "Jacques Rene <b><u>Chirac</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s security forces held mass executions in soccer stadiums which targeted dissidents  such as singer Victor Jara. \u201cThe brick\u201d was a book produced to aid this man by Milton Friedman and the Chicago Boys. This man commanded the DINA secret police and was a key player in Operation Condor. Henry Kissinger endorsed his 1973 coup against Salvador Allende. For the point, name this dictator of Chile.", "answer": "Augusto <b><u>Pinochet</u></b> Ugarte", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This battle is the subject of two popular songs which describe stepping on an alligator\u2019s tail  to form a makeshift cannon and running \u201cwhere the rabbits wouldn\u2019t go.\u201d Slaves who defected during this battle were evacuated to Bermuda. This battle was where Jean Lafitte's pirates came to the aid of the Americans against Edward Pakenham. For the point, name this victory for Andrew Jackson that was fought two weeks after the formal end of the War of 1812, in Louisiana.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>New Orleans</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s attempts to keep the country gentlemen who opposed him in check led him to oppose the Peerage Bill. The Porteous Riots took place during his term, and he helped England overcome the South Sea Bubble disaster by instituting the \u201csinking fund\u201d in his role as  Chancellor of the Exchequer. This man oversaw the War of Jenkins\u2019s Ear and the \u201cWhig  Ascendancy\u201d following the death of Queen Anne. For the point, name this prime minister to George I and II, the first person to hold that role.", "answer": "Robert <b><u>Walpole</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Sources for these actions were the pamphlets <em>Counterattack</em> and <em>RedChannels</em>. A signal that the time of these actions had ended came when John F. Kennedy defied American Legion picketers to attend a showing of <em>Spartacus</em>. Dalton Trumbo openly took credit for <em>Exodus</em>, also ending the era of this phenomenon, which began when ten witness refused to testify to HUAC in 1947. For the point, name this procedure under which Communists were not permitted to work in the entertainment industry.", "answer": "<b><u>blacklist</u></b>s of Communists in Hollywood", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A participant in this event proposed that \u201cJustice, Christian Charity, and Peace\u201d be advanced at this event by creating a Holy Alliance. This event extended universal recognition to the House of Orange\u2019s rule in the Netherlands. The Duke of Wellington replaced Lord Castlereagh as  British representative to this event, also attended by Alexander I of Russia and France\u2019s Talleyrand. For the point, name this meeting which convened in 1814 to organized the \u201cconcert of Europe\u201d following the fall of Napoleon.", "answer": "<b><u>Congress of Vienna</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This organization was supported by \u201cPrince of Plasterers\u201d Andrew Garvey. This  organization\u2019s last gasp of power was under Carmine De Sapio. George Plunkitt defended this organization\u2019s participation in \"honest graft.\" Fernando Wood was the first mayor from this group, that was represented as a tiger in political cartoons. For the point, name this New York political machine run by \"Boss\" Tweed which controlled the city Democratic Party in part until the 1950s.", "answer": "<b><u>Tammany</u></b> Hall", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "James Boswell\u2019s \u201caccount\u201d of this island discusses the briefly successful republican movement led here by Pasquale Paoli, who ended five hundred years of domination of this island by Genoa. The Battle of Punto Novo ended the republic here. This island is now controlled by France, and is found to the north of the Italian-controlled Sardinia. For the point, name this large Mediterranean island where Napoleon was born.", "answer": "<b><u>Corsica</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One work by this man states that charters don\u2019t give rights, but take them away. This man denounced the Bible as \"fabulous mythology\" in his pamphlet advocating deism, <em>The Age of</em>  <em>Reason</em>. This man denounced the \u201cabsurdity\u201d of an island ruling a continent in a series designed for distribution in both England and the newly independent colonies. For the point, name this author of <em>Common Sense</em>, a leading propagandist of the American Revolution.", "answer": "Thomas <b><u>Paine</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Guibert of Nogent was a noted chronicler of this campaign. During a part of this campaign,  Jews were massacred in Metz and other cities in the Rhineland as part of the People\u2019s Crusade. A piece of the Holy Lance was found during the Siege of Antioch during this Crusade. Led by Godfrey of Bouillon and Bohemond of Taranto, this Crusade took control of a holy city from the Fatimid Dynasty, establishing the Kingdom of Jerusalem. For ten points, name this Crusade called for by Urban II at the Council of Clermont.", "answer": "<b><u>First</u></b> Crusade  [Dan Puma]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During this war, the Kagnew Battalion captured prisoners in the Battle of Pork Chop Hill. Fighter jets met at MiG Alley during this war, which included the Bodo League and No Gun Ri  massacres. This war\u2019s early phases involved the challenge of crossing the Pusan Perimeter. A commander in this war was removed for advocating the use of nuclear weapons against China, and replaced with Matthew Ridgway. For the point, name this war in which the amphibious landing at Inchon took place and Douglas MacArthur was relieved of command.", "answer": "<b><u>Korean</u></b> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The colonial effects of this event included Leisler's Rebellion in New York. This event was secured at the Battle of the Diamond and Battle of the Boyne, and it was ratified along with the English Bill of Rights. Diehard opponents of this event formed the Jacobite movement. England\u2019s last Catholic ruler was deposed by this event. For the point, name this 1688 uprising which dismissed James II from the British throne in favor of William and Mary.", "answer": "<b><u>Glorious Revolution</u></b> [accept <b><u>Revolution of 1688</u></b> before the year is read]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man was Chief Justice when the <em>West Coast Hotel</em> decision became the \u201cswitch in time  that saved nine.\u201d This man organized the Washington Naval Conference as Harding and Coolidge's Secretary of State. This man\u2019s snub of Hiram Johnson may have cost him the 1916 election. In 1935, his majority opinion invalidated the National Industrial Recovery Act's  \u201cvoluntary codes\u201d in the \"sick chicken\" case. For the point, name this Supreme Court Chief Justice of the 1930s, a former Republican who initially opposed the New Deal.", "answer": "Charles Evans <b><u>Hughes</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s 1959 marriage to the daughter of a flour executive brought the first commoner on record into his royal family. This man went on television after the 2011 Tohoku earthquake, breaking protocol in a sign that he wishes to open direct communication between the  Chrysanthemum Throne and the populace. This man\u2019s reign will be known as the \"Heisei\" era after he dies. For the point, name this man who took office in 1989 as Hirohito\u2019s successor as emperor of Japan.", "answer": "<b><u>Akihito</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This person was criticized by a February 2015 attack ad for being involved in a foundation that took twenty-five million dollars from the government of Saudi Arabia. In August 2014, this  person said \u201cdon't do stupid stuff\u201d is \u201cnot an organizing principle.\u201d This author of the memoir <em>Hard Choices</em> was criticized in March 2015 for using a private e-mail address while serving as Secretary of State. For the point, name this former First Lady, a leading 2016 Presidential candidate.", "answer": "<b><u>H</u></b>illary Rodham <b><u>Clinton</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>Clinton</u></b>]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This society used precise 1 to 2 to 4 ratios to make bricks. This society was first excavated in 1827 by Charles Masso. The Great Bath is a relic of this society, which used some of the first known sewer systems. A city from this society has a name meaning \"Mound of the Dead.\" This society included the cities of Mohenjo-daro and Harappa. For the point, what early South Asian civilization is named for a river in present-day Pakistan?", "answer": "<b><u>Indus</u></b> River/Valley civilization [or <b><u>Harappa</u></b>n until it is read]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man wrote a thesis on nineteenth-century Europe called <em>A WorldRestored</em>. He tried to prevent American media from publicizing the bombing of neutral Cambodia and similarly tried to hide the outbreak of the Yom Kippur War. This diplomat met secretly with Zhou Enlai (JOE en-LAI), opening the door for Nixon\u2019s visit to China. He was the co-recipient of a Nobel Peace Prize, with Le Duc Tho (lay Duck though), for ending American involvement in Vietnam. For the point, name this German-born security advisor and Secretary of State under Nixon and Ford.", "answer": "Henry <b><u>Kissinger</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This woman once publicly whipped Johann Most for failing to support her actions. This publisher of<em> MotherEarth</em> gave lectures which influenced assassin Leon Czolgosz (CHOL-gosh). With lover Alexander Berkman, she plotted to intervene in the Homestead Strike by assassinating Henry Clay Frick. She later wrote <em>My Disillusionment in Russia</em> about the  shortcomings of Communism.For the point, name this leader of American anarchism in the early twentieth century.", "answer": "Emma <b><u>Goldman</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was criticized for saying that people who don\u2019t study hard \u201cget stuck in Iraq\u201d and  for the delivery of his \u201creporting for duty\u201d speech. This man led a committee that accused Oliver North of tolerating drug smuggling. He became nationally prominent in 1971, when he testified before the Senate as a delegate from Vietnam Veterans Against the War. He was mocked by the wearing of band-aids, a reference to conspiracy theories about his Purple Hearts, and targeted by ads from Swift Boat Veterans for Truth. For the point, name this current Secretary of State.", "answer": "John Forbes <b><u>Kerry</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "These devices are used in confocal scanning microscopes. The \u201cwiggler\u201d version of this device was built by John Madey. These items were patented by Gordon Gould. The Albert Einstein paper proposing the feasibility of these devices defined the A and B coefficients as an  electron\u2019s probability of moving between states and emitting a photon. For the point, name these devices which produce coherent beams of light from stimulated emission.", "answer": "<b><u>laser</u></b>s", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "This man won the Presidency partially due to the Whigs bleeding votes in New York to the  Liberty Party of James G. Birney. This man\u2019s platform included the establishment of an  independent subtreasury. This man, the original \u201cDark Horse,\u201d was given the nicknames \u201cYoung Hickory\u201d and \u201cNapoleon of the stump\u201d during his campaign. He resolved the Oregon boundary dispute and annexed Texas, which led to a war. For the point, name this one-term President who met all his campaign goals and oversaw the Mexican War.", "answer": "James Knox <b><u>Polk</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "After this man\u2019s sudden death, he was succeeded by his son Ellac, who could not regain the momentum this man had prior to his loss at the Catalaunian Plains. This man faced a Visigoth-Roman alliance led by Theodoric and Flavius Aetius. Earlier, this brother of Bleda was persuaded to abandon plans to sack Rome by a personal plea from Pope Leo I. For the point, name this \"scourge of God\" who ravaged Europe in the fifth century CE as the leader of the Huns.", "answer": "<b><u>Attila</u></b> the Hun", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man was accused of ripping off moves from \u201cBig Mama\u201d Thornton when he covered a  song she wrote. This man\u2019s songs include once begging the listener \u201cnot to do what your big sister done\u201d and an attempt to address social problems of the late 1960s, \u201cIn the Ghetto.\u201d This man also starred in the films <em>Blue Hawaii</em> and <em>Viva Las Vegas</em>. For the point, name this singer of  \u201cDon\u2019t Be Cruel,\u201d \"Hound Dog,\" and \u201cJailhouse Rock,\u201d an icon of the early rock and roll era who later died at Graceland.", "answer": "Elvis <b><u>Presley</u></b> [or <b><u>Elvis</u></b>]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A candidate in this political party controversially won a 1988 presidential election after computer systems crashed. Hand picked successors in this party were given approval in the <em>dedazo</em> process. A member of this party nationalized the oil company PEMEX. That man was Lorenzo Cardenas. This party lost power after the election of PAN candidate Vicente Fox in 2000. For ten points, name this political party that for much of the 20th century dominated Mexican politics.", "answer": "<b><u>PRI</u></b> [or <b><u>Partido Revolucionario Institutional</u></b>; or <b><u>Institutional Revolutionary</u></b> <b><u>Party</u></b>]  <u>[Pum</u>a]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The center of this sea hosted \u201cRebirth Island,\u201d which was once thought to be a secure storage  facility for botulism and other bioweapons. This sea is the source of \u201csalt storms\u201d which have affected food crops in Karakalpakstan and made non-cotton industries unviable. After water that replenished this sea was diverted into the Karakum Canal for irrigation, the Amu Darya river was unable to maintain its water level. For the point, name this sea which once straddled the border of Kazakhstan and Uzbekistan and has effectively disappeared.", "answer": "<b><u>Aral</u></b> Sea", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s deputy Hans Schweitzer was known by the nickname \u201cMjolnir.\u201d This man was an early advocate of renewed warfare in his \u201cSportpalast Speech.\u201d This man organized \u201cimmorality trials\u201d against nuns and clerics as part of the \u201cKirchenkampf\u201d or anti-church campaign that he led. This man and his wife Magda poisoned their six children before committing suicide in 1945 in the Fuhrerbunker, where he was the designated successor to Hitler. For the point, name this Nazi propaganda master.", "answer": "Joseph <b><u>Goebbels</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man led the army which routed Spain at the Battle of the Dunes. This close ideological ally of Henry Ireton increased his control over first the Rump and then the Barebones  Parliaments. This man was responsible for Irish massacres at Wexford and Drogheda (DROY-duh). This military opponent of Prince Rupert led the Eastern Association\u2019s cavalry at Marston Moor. For the point, name this Roundhead who became Lord Protector of England following the overthrow of Charles I in the Civil War.", "answer": "Oliver <b><u>Cromwell</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A bad DNA test in 2014 suggested that this person was Polish immigrant Aaron Kosminski. This person has also been identified with Montague Druitt and John Pizer, and perhaps his most intriguing identity is the Duke of Clarence. William Gull, the royal physician, is sometimes called this person due to apparent knowledge of surgical techniques. This person killed Mary Kelly and at least four other Whitechapel prostitutes in 1888. For the point, give this name used for the unknown killer who terrorized London.", "answer": "<b><u>Jack the Ripper</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A novel satirizing this country, titled for traditional monsters here, includes a businessman  who proposes that the unemployed be gassed and made into a food. This country\u2019s literature  includes a genre of stray thoughts known as \u201czuihitsu,\u201d which was used to write <em>The Pillow</em>  <em>Book</em>. This country developed the dramatic forms of \u201cbunraku\u201d puppet theater as well as \u201cnoh\u201d  and \u201ckabuki.\u201d For the point, name this country where Lady Murasaki wrote the early novel <em>Tale</em>  <em>of Genji.</em>", "answer": "<b><u>Japan</u></b> [or <b><u>Nippon</u></b>]", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This historically significant place is depicted indoors underneath a billowing white curtain in an unfinished painting. An open window in the background of a painting depicting this place shows a lightning bolt which seems to point out the hand of Jean-Sylvain Bailly. This place is shown in that 1794 painting by Jacques-Louis David, who chronicled many events of the Revolution including the gathering here. For the point, name this sporting venue where members of the Third Estate took an oath.", "answer": "<b><u>tennis court</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This author of <em>Industryand Humanity</em> lost one election after he said that he \u201cwould not give a five cent-piece\u201d for unemployment relief. Besides that election loss in 1930 to R.B. Bennett, this politician had earlier lost power when Governor General Julian Byng made his longtime rival, Arthur Meighen, prime minister. This Liberal politician served as prime minister during World War Two. For 10 points, name this politician, Canada\u2019s longest serving Prime Minister.", "answer": "William Lyon Mackenzie <b><u>King</u> </b> [Patrick Liao]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s opposition to the planned sharing and co-crewing of Polaris missiles led to his 1963 withdrawal of his country from NATO leader, the same year that he opposed British entry to the European Economic Community. This man was succeeded by his longtime deputy Georges Pompidou when he resigned the presidency just after a failed referendum in the light of the May 1968 protests. He signed the Evian Accords, ending the Algerian war. For the point, name this architect and first president of the Fifth Republic and Free French leader during World War II.", "answer": "Charles Andre Joseph Marie <b><u>de Gaulle</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This political cause was pseudonymously taken up by future playwright Mercy Otis Warren and supported by the William West marchers in Rhode Island. The collective pen names \u201cCato\u201d  and \u201cBrutus\u201d were used by members of this loose group, which rallied behind the quip \u201cI smell a rat\u201d issued by Patrick Henry. Many members of this group joined the new Democratic- Republican Party alongside their chief opponent, James Madison. For the point, name this group of people who opposed ratifying of the Constitution.", "answer": "<b><u>anti-Federal</u></b>ists [accept <b><u>opposition to ratifying the constitution</u></b> or equivalents therein befo<u>re the word \u201c</u>Opposed\u201d]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In the 1990s, this company branched into comic books, publishing licensed series based on <em>Jurassic Park</em> and <em>The X-Files</em>. This company once issued alternate versions of its main product on \u201cTiffany\u201d stock and created the supplemental \u201cTraded\u201d sets every year. Since 2009, this company has again held a monopoly on its main product, a market which Donruss and Fleer entered to compete with this company in 1981. For the point, name this longest-standing, and now only, manufacturer of licensed Major League Baseball trading cards.", "answer": "<b><u>Topps</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "In the months before this year\u2019s election, the author of <em>The Prospect</em> was prosecuted for attacking the incumbent President. This election partly turned on a party leader writing a fifty-page letter that attempted to get Charles Cotesworth Pinckney elected President. Chaos in the voting system for this election resulted in the Twelfth Amendment\u2019s passage soon afterwards. For the point, name this election in which the U.S. peacefully transferred power for the first time as Thomas Jefferson unseated John Adams.", "answer": "United States Presidential election of <b><u>1800</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Paul Henderson played this sport, and was a star of the Summit Series contested in this sport.  Stars in this sport included Vladimir Tretiak and forward Valeri Kharlamov, in a year when Finland won the silver medal in this sport following a surprise entrant to the gold-medal game. Jim Craig and Mike Eruzione played this sport in the Olympics under coach Herb Brooks. For the point, name this sport in which the all-amateur U.S. team defeated the heavily favored Soviets at Lake Placid in 1980\u2019s \u201cMiracle on Ice.\u201d", "answer": "ice <b><u>hockey</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man was known as \u201cRaven\u201d to the Cherokee following his adoption by chief John Jolly. This man attacked William Stanberry with a cane after being accused of corruption, and he was in executive office when the Regulator-Moderator war erupted in his state. This man resigned rather than endorse the Confederacy, decades after he led a militia that won the Battle of San Jacinto over Santa Anna. For the point, name this ally of Stephen F. Austin in the creation of the Republic of Texas.", "answer": "Samuel <b><u>Houston</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Members of this religion were forbidden to ride horses and had to use donkeys instead, and  could not build houses taller than those of the majority religion\u2019s members. Members of this religion were hit with a stick while paying their jizyatax and were sometimes attacked by having their kushtis torn off. Most members of this religion fled their persecution by Muslim dynasties and became Parsees in India. For the point, name this former majority religion of Iran, which makes use of towers of silence and worships Ahura Mazda.", "answer": "<b><u>Zoroastrian</u></b>ism", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Charles Rangel periodically introduces bills to bring back this procedure. This procedure was often protested by the burning of cards, which became the subject of the free speech case <em>U.S.v.</em> <em>O'Brien</em>. Jimmy Carter pardoned nearly everyone who avoided this procedure, including those who fled to Canada or fraudulently obtained 4-F status. For the point, name this procedure which forcibly added men to the fighting ranks, most recently during the Vietnam War.", "answer": "military <b><u>draft</u></b> [or <b><u>conscription</u></b>, etc.]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s court is where the concept of lowercase letters was first developed. This man, who received an elephant from Harun al-Rashid, patronized the cultural work of Alcuin of York in a namesake \u201crenaissance.\u201d This organizer of the Saxon Crusade appears in the <em>Song of Roland</em> as the commander of the army which is ambushed at the climactic battle. For the point, name this son of Pippin the Short who was crowned emperor by Leo III on Christmas Day 800.", "answer": "<b><u>Charlemagne</u> </b>[or <b><u>Charles the Great</u></b>; or <b><u>Carolus Magnus;</u></b> or <b><u>Karl der Grosse</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Craterus's son Alexander launched a brief anti-Macedonian tyranny from this city in 252 BC; a hundred years later, this city was totally destroyed during the Roman conquest of Greece. This city was the namesake of a 395 to 387 BC war which ended with the King's Peace and the alliance of Persia and Sparta. This city originally colonized Syracuse and was ruled by the Bacchiadae for several centuries. This city, the namesake of non-Doric, non-Ionic columns, was mythically ruled by Sisyphus. For the point, name this Greek city found on a namesake isthmus.", "answer": "<b><u>Corinth</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This office is held during caretaker periods by the Country Party. This office was held by a  man who praised the middle class in the \u201cForgotten People\u201d speech, and by a man who  disappeared while swimming in the ocean. This office, held by Robert Menzies and Harold Holt, has long been dominated by the Liberal and Labor parties. In the 2000s, the holder of this office formally apologized for the Stolen Generations. For the point, name this head of state, an office in which Tony Abbott succeeded Kevin Rudd in 2013.", "answer": "<b><u>Prime Minister of Australia</u></b> [do not accept \u201cPresident of Australia\u201d]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "This man was accused of being a sorcerer who removed his head at night and wandered his palace in the <em>Secret History</em> of Procopius. This man patronized Tribonian to compile existing laws. This emperor\u2019s army won battles such as Volturnus under one of his generals, Narses,  though his main challenge was calming his capital\u2019s population by handing out bags of gold during the Nika Riots. For the point, name this husband of Theodora who issued a namesake \u201ccode\u201d and patronized the construction of the Hagia Sophia as a great Byzantine emperor.", "answer": "<b><u>Justinian</u></b> I [or <b><u>Justinian</u></b> the Great]", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}